让我们回顾一下我们在本次讲座中学到的一些重要事项。在上一讲中
Let's recap some of the big things that we've learned in this lecture. In the previous lecture
我们讨论了正向运动学函数;这就是K的功能。它的论点是Q和
we discussed the forward kinematic function; that's the function K. Its argument is Q and
这是关节角度的矢量，它的长度为N的向量，其中N是关节的数量
that's the vector of joint angles, its vector of length N, where N is the number of joints
机器人有。正向运动功能的结果是机器人的姿势
that the robot has. The result of the forward kinematic function is the pose of the robots
末端效应器，我称之为ksiN。正向运动学采用关节角度并给出
end effector, which I call here ksiN. Forward kinematics takes the joint angles and gives
我们机器人末端效应器的姿势。
us the robot end effector pose.
在这个讲座中，我们讨论了逆运动学函数，这里显示为K.
In this lecture we've discussed the inverse kinematic function that's shown here as K
到负一号。它在机器人末端执行器姿势上运行并告诉我们关节角度
to the minus one. It operates on the robot end effector pose and tells us the joint angles
要达到那个姿势。逆是不唯一的。对于特定的机器人端
required to achieve that pose. The inverse is not unique. For a particular robot end
效应器姿势，可以有多组关节角度来实现这一点
effector pose, there can be multiple sets of joint angles which will achieve that particular
姿势，对于我们的小二连杆机器人，这里显示了两种可能的配置。
pose, for our little two link robot, there are two possible configurations shown here.
对于我们的六连环Puma机器人，它在三维空间中运行，实际上
For our six link Puma robot, which operates in three dimensional space, there are in fact
六种可能的解决方
six possible solutions.
有几种方法可以解决特定的逆运动学问题
There are several approaches to solving the inverse kinematic problem for a particular
机器人。对于像两个链接示例这样的简单机器人，我们使用几何解决方案
robot. For a simple robot like the two link example, we use a geometric solution and that
需要一些直觉和一些见解，它涉及定义特定的三角形，
requires some intuition and some insight, it involves defining particular triangles,
引入新的角度并按顺序应用许多简单的三角关系
introducing new angles and applying a number of simple trigonometric relationships in order
解决我们感兴趣的关节角度，在这种情况下Q1和Q2作为函数
to solve for the joint angles we're interested in, in this case Q1 and Q2 as a function of
末端执行器姿势XY和机器人的恒定链路长度A1和A2。我们就这么做了
the end effector pose XY and the robot's constant link lengths A1 and A2. We right down the
正向运动学方程，这里给出了末端效应器姿势X和Y
forward kinematic equations, which here give us the end effector pose X and Y in terms
关节角度然后与大量的操纵再次与一些
of the joint angles and then with a large amount of manipulation and again with some
洞察力和直觉，我们可以写出给我们机器人关节角度的方程式。
insight and intuition, we can write down equations which give us the robot joint angles.
机器人逆运动学分析解决方案涉及的步骤涉及到
The steps involved in the analytic solution for robot inverse kinematics involves the
以下步骤;首先我们需要一个机器人模型，我们需要知道位置和
following steps; firstly we need a model of the robot, we need to know the position and
关节相对于链节的方向。我们需要知道它的长度
orientation of the joints with respect to the links. We need to know the lengths of
链接等。从那里我们提取了许多方程式，我们试图解决
the links and so on. From that we extract a number of equations and we attempt to solve
对于未知的关节变量。正如我之前所说，它需要一些人类的洞察力
for the unknown joint variables. As I said before, it requires some human insight, although
对于特定的机器人或特定机器人，它可以使用计算机代数技术自动化
it can be automated using computer algebra techniques for particular robots or particular
机器人类。
classes of robots.
分析解决方案的巨大优势在于它明确地向您显示了多种配置
The great advantages of the analytic solution is it explicitly shows you the multiple configurations
机器人，让您选择将为您提供配置的关节角度
of the robot and lets you choose the joint angles that will give you the configuration
你要的那个。对于Puma560机器人，它允许您明确选择左手配置
that you want. For the Puma 560 robot it allows you to explicitly choose a left handed configuration
或右手配置或肘部向上或肘部向下。另一个优点是
or a right handed configuration or the elbow up or the elbow down. Another advantage is
解决方案非常紧凑，执行速度快。你可以得到结果方程
that the solutions are very compact and fast to execute. You can take the resulting equations
并且您可以使用您喜欢的编程语言对它们进行编码，然后执行它们
and you can code them up in your favorite programming language and they will execute
非常非常快然而，分析方法越来越难以作为数量
very, very quickly. However the analytic approach is increasingly difficult as the number of
对于六连杆机器人来说，关节增加并且需要做很多工作。幸好
joints increases and takes quite a lot of work to do it for a six link robot. Fortunately
许多聪明人已经在很多，几十年的时间里研究过这个问题和解决方案
a lot of smart people have looked at this problem over many, many decades and solutions
因为几乎所有的机器人都已经衍生出来并在文献的某个地方出版。
for almost all robots have been derived and are published somewhere in the literature.
分析解决方案的替代方案是数值解决方案，这是适用的
An alternative to the analytic solution is the numerical solution and that's applicable
当分析解决方案不存在或分析解决方案太难以解决时
when the analytic solution doesn't exist or the analytic solution is just too hard to
弄清楚。它依赖于我们总能确定正向运动学的事实
figure out. It relies on the fact that we can always determine the forward kinematics
机器人，这是相对简单的，我们在前面讨论过
of the robot, that’s relatively straightforward to do and we talked about that in the previous
演讲。我们知道我们希望机器人结束的姿势
lecture. We know the pose that we want the robot end
效应器实现哪个被称为ksi*，但我们需要做的就是调整关节
effector to achieve which is called ksi*, but all we need to do is adjust the joint
角度Q直到ksi与ksi*匹配，我们可以在数学上将其作为优化
angles Q until ksi matches ksi* and we can pose this mathematically as an optimization
这里写的问题非常正式。我们展示了如何使用MATLAB和机器人技术
problem written very formally here. And we showed how we can use MATLAB and the robotics
工具箱确定双链机器人和六连杆机器人的数值解。
toolbox to determine the numerical solution for a two link robot and for a six link robot.
数值解有一些缺点。你需要小心选择
There are some disadvantages with the numerical solution. You need to be careful about choosing
用于优化器的初始关节角度集。你无法保证
the initial set of joint angles that you use for your optimizer. You can't guarantee that
优化器将找到您感兴趣的特定机器人配置。如果
the optimizer will find the particular robot configuration that you're interested in. If
你想要一个左撇子配置，你不能保证优化器会找到它
you wanted a left handed configuration, you can't guarantee the optimizer will find that
特殊配置，取决于您选择的初始关节角度。它也可以
particular configuration, it depends on your choice of initial joint angles. It can also
计算上很昂贵。这是一个迭代算法，迭代次数取决于
be computationally expensive. It's an iterative algorithm and the number of iterations depends
关于你的初始关节角度有多好以及计算费用可能不合适
on how good your initial set of joint angles is and that computational expense maybe inappropriate
在一个硬的实时系统中，你需要在一个小的内部计算反向运动学
in a hard, real time system where you need to compute inverse kinematics within a small
和有限的时间。我们讨论了如何为机器人端创建平滑路径
and finite amount of time. We talked about how to create smooth paths for the robot end
效应器从一个姿势移动到另一个姿势，我们介绍了两种方法。
effector moving from one pose to another and we introduced two approaches to doing this.
第一个是所谓的“联合插值路径”。我们采取最初的姿势和决赛
The first is what's called a "Joint Interpolated Path." We take the initial pose and final
姿势，我们使用反向运动学来确定关节角度的初始和最终集合，
pose and we use inverse kinematics to determine the initial and final sets of joint angles,
然后我们在这两组关节角度之间进行平滑插值，这是相对的
then we smoothly interpolate between those two sets of joint angles and that's relatively
直截了当。
straightforward to do.
这样做的缺点是我们不能保证机器人会沿着直线前进
The disadvantage of this is we can't guarantee that the robot will follow a straight line
三维空间中的路径。我们也无法保证末端效应器的定位
path in three dimensional space. We also can't guarantee that the end effector orientation
在这条道路上的每一点都是我们理想的价值;然而是联合插值路径
will be our desired value at every point along that path; however joint interpolated paths
计算相对便宜，因为我们只是插入关节角度向量
are relatively cheap to compute because we're only interpolating joint angle vectors at
永远的一步。另一种方法是计算笛卡尔插值路径以及我们的路径
ever time step. An alternative is to compute a Cartesian interpolated path and what we
这里是针对沿着轨迹的每个点，我们在初始和最终之间进行插值
do here is for every point along the trajectory we interpolate between the initial and final
末端效应器的姿势。对于每个插值姿势，我们然后计算逆运动学
end effector pose. For each interpolated pose we then compute the inverse kinematics to
找到适合该特定时间步长的关节角度。
find the joint angles that are appropriate at that particular time step.
这种技术的优点是它允许三维直线路径
The advantage of this technique is that it allows for straight line paths in three dimensional
空间。它还确保末端执行器在每个点都具有所需的方向
space. It also ensures that the end effector has got the desired orientation at every point
沿着轨道。
along the trajectory.
缺点是计算上它更昂贵。我们需要插值
The disadvantage is that computationally it's much more expensive. We need to interpolate
姿势和涉及内插平移分量和旋转
poses and that involves interpolating the translational component and the rotational
组件，实际上可能涉及从旋转矩阵转换为四元数插值
component and that might in fact involve converting from rotation matrix to a quaternion interpolating
四元数然后将其转换回旋转矩阵，然后我们必须
the quaternion and then transforming that back to a rotation matrix, then we have to
在每个时间步执行逆运动学。涉及更多的计算，
perform the inverse kinematics at every single time step. So much more computation involved,
好处是我们可以保证三维空间中的直线路径。
upside is that we can guarantee straight line paths in three dimensional space.